<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      version="5.0"
      xml:id="enter-environment">

  <title>Enter Environment</title>

  <para>
    Welcome to the third Nix pill. In the previous <link
    linkend="install-on-your-running-system">second pill</link> we have
    installed Nix on our running system. Now we can finally play with it a
    little, things also apply to NixOS users.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Enter the environment</title>

    <para>
      In the previous pill we created a nix user, so let's start by switching
      user with <literal>su - nix</literal>. If your
      <literal>~/.profile</literal> got evaluated, then your should now be able
      to run commands like <literal>nix-env</literal> and
      <literal>nix-store</literal>.
    </para>

    <para>
      If that's not the case:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/source-nix.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      I remind you, <literal>~/.nix-profile/etc</literal> points to the nix-1.7
      derivation. At this point, we are in our nix user profile.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Install something</title>

    <para>
      Finally something practical! Installation in the nix environment is an
      interesting process. Let's install nix-repl, a simple command line tool
      for playing with the Nix language. Yes, Nix is a <link xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nix/manual/#idm47361539226272">
        pure, lazy, functional language</link>, not only a set of tools to
      manage derivations.
    </para>

    <para>
      Back to the installation:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/install-repl.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Now you can run nix-repl. Things to notice:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          We did install software as user, only for the nix user.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          It created a new user environment. That's a new generation of our
          nix user profile.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <link
          xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nix/manual/#sec-nix-env">nix-env</link>
          tool manages environments, profiles and their generations.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          We installed nix-repl by derivation name minus the version. I repeat:
          we did specify the <emphasis role="bold">derivation name</emphasis>
          (minus the version) to install.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      We can list generations without walking through the /nix hierarchy:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/list-generations.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      List installed derivations:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/list-installed-derivations.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      So, where did nix-repl really get installed?
      <literal>which nix-repl</literal> is
      <literal>~/.nix-profile.bin.nix-repl</literal> which points to the store.
      We can also list the derivation paths with nix-env -q --out-path. So
      that's how those derivation paths are called: the
      <emphasis role="bold">output</emphasis> of a build.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Path merging</title>

    <para>
      At this point you sure have the necessity to run "man". Even if you
      already have man system-wide outside of the nix environment, you can
      install and use it within nix with <literal>nix-env -i man</literal>. As
      usual, a new generation will be created, and ~/.nix-profile will point to
      it.
    </para>

    <para>
      Lets inspect the <link
      xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nix/manual/#sec-profiles">profile</link>
      a bit:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/ls-nix-profile.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Now that's interesting. When only nix-1.7 was installed, bin/ was a
      symlink to nix-1.7. Now it's a real directory, no symlink.
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/ls-profile-bin.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      All clear. nix-env merged the paths from the installed derivations.
      <literal>which man</literal> points to the nix profile, rather than the
      system man, because <literal>~/.nix-profile/bin</literal> is at the head
      of <literal>$PATH</literal>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Rollback / switch generation</title>

    <para>
      The last command installed "man". We should be at generation #3, unless
      you changed something in the middle. Let's say we want to rollback to the
      old generation:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/rollback.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Now <literal>nix-env -q</literal> does not list "man" anymore.
      <literal>ls -l `which man`</literal> should now be your system installed
      one.
    </para>

    <para>
      Enough with the joke, let's go back to the last generation:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/generation-3.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      I invite you to read the manpage of nix-env. nix-env requires an operation
      to perform, then there are common options for all operations, and there
      are options specific to an operation.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can of course also <link
        xlink:href="https://nixos.org/nix/manual/#operation-uninstall">
      uninstall</link> and <link
      xlink:href="https://nixos.org/nix/manual/#operation-upgrade">upgrade</link> packages.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Querying the store</title>

    <para>
      So far we learned how to query and manipulate the environment. But all
      of the environment components point to the store.
    </para>

    <para>
      To query and manipulate the store, there's the
      <literal>nix-store</literal> command. We can do neat things, but we'll
      only see some queries for now.
    </para>

    <para>
      Show direct runtime dependencies of nix-repl:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/references.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      The argument to nix-store can be anything as long as it points to the
      nix store. It will follow symlinks.
    </para>

    <para>
      It may not make sense for you right now, but let's print reverse
      dependencies of nix-repl:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/referrers.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Did you expect it? Our environments depend upon nix-repl. Yes, the
      environments are in the store, and since there are symlinks to nix-repl,
      therefore the environment depends upon nix-repl
    </para>

    <para>
      It lists two environments, generation 2 and generation 3.
    </para>

    <para>
      The manifest.nix file contains metadata about the environment, such as
      which derivations are installed. So that nix-env can list them, upgrade
      or remove them. Guess what, the current manifest.nix can be found in
      <literal>~/.nix-profile/manifest.nix</literal>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Closures</title>

    <para>
      The closures of a derivation is a list of all dependencies, recursively,
      down to the bare minimum necessary to use that derivation.
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/nix-store.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Copying all those derivations to the nix store of another machine makes
      you able to run "man" out of the box on that other machine. That's the
      base of nix deployment, you can already foresee the potential when
      deploying software in the cloud (hint:
      <literal>nix-copy-closures</literal> and
      <literal>nix-store --export</literal>).
    </para>

    <para>
      A nicer view of the closure:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/nix-store-tree.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      With the above command, you can know exactly why a
      <emphasis role="bold">runtime</emphasis> dependency, being it direct or
      indirect, has been picked for a given derivation.
    </para>

    <para>
      Same applies to environments of course. As an exercise run
      <literal>nix-store -q --tree ~/.nix-profile</literal>, see that the
      first children are direct dependencies of the user environment:
      the installed derivations, and the manifest.nix.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Dependency resolution</title>

    <para>
      There isn't anything like apt which solves a SAT problem in order to
      satisfy dependencies with lower and upper bounds on versions. Because
      there's no need. A derivation X depends on derivation Y, always.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Fancy disrupt</title>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/uninstall-all.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Ops, that uninstalled all derivations from the environment, including
      nix. We are not able to run nix-env, what now?
    </para>

    <para>
      Environments are a convenience for the user, but Nix is still there, in
      the store!
    </para>

    <para>
      First pick one nix-1.7 derivation:
      <literal>ls /nix/store/*nix-1.7</literal>, say
      /nix/store/g21di262aql6xskx15z3qiw3zh3wmjlb-nix-1.7.
    </para>

    <para>
      The first possibility is to rollback:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/nix-env-rollback.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      The second possibility is to install nix, thus creating a new generation:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/install.txt" parse="text" /></screen>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Channels</title>

    <para>
      So where are we getting packages from? We said something already in
      <link linkend="install-on-your-running-system">pill 2</link>.
      There's a list of channels from which we get packages, usually we use a
      single channel. The tool to manage channels is
      <link xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nix/manual/#sec-nix-channel">nix-channel</link>.
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/channel-list.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      That's basically the contents of <literal>~/.nix-channels</literal>.
      Note: <literal>~/.nix-channels</literal> is not a symlink to the
      nix store!
    </para>

    <para>
      To update the channel run <literal>nix-channel --update</literal>.
      It will download the new nix expressions (descriptions of the packages),
      create a new generation of the channels profile and unpack under
      <literal>~/.nix-defexpr/channels</literal>.
    </para>

    <para>
      That's much similar to apt-get update.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>
      We learned how to query the user environment and to manipulate it by
      installing and uninstalling software. Upgrading software is as straight
      as it gets by reading
      <link xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nix/manual/#idm47361539520832">the manual</link>
      (<literal>nix-env -u '*'</literal> will upgrade all packages in the
      environment).
    </para>

    <para>
      Everytime we change the environment, a new generation gets created.
      Switching between generations is easy and immediate.
    </para>

    <para>
      Then we queried the store. We inspected the dependencies and reverse
      dependencies of store paths.
    </para>

    <para>
      We still see symlinks to compose paths from the nix store, our lovely
      trick.
    </para>

    <para>
      Quick analogy with programming languages. You have the heap with all the
      objects, that's the nix store. You have objects that point to other
      objects, those are the derivations. Will be this the right path?
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Next pill</title>

    <para>
      ...we will learn the basics of the Nix language. The Nix language is used
      to describe how to build derivations, and it's the base for everything
      else including NixOS. Therefore it's very important to understand the
      syntax and the semantics.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
