<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      version="5.0"
      xml:id="enter-environment">

  <title>Enter the Environment</title>

  <para>
    Welcome to the third Nix pill. In the <link
    linkend="install-on-your-running-system">second pill</link> we
    installed Nix on our running system. Now we can finally play with it a
    little, these things also apply to NixOS users.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Enter the environment</title>

    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">If you're using NixOS, you can skip to the <link
      linkend="install-something">next</link> step.</emphasis>
    </para>

    <para>
      In the previous article we created a Nix user, so let's start by switching
      to it with <command>su - nix</command>. If your
      <filename>~/.profile</filename> got evaluated, then you should now be able
      to run commands like <literal>nix-env</literal> and
      <literal>nix-store</literal>.
    </para>

    <para>
      If that's not the case:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/source-nix.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      To remind you, <literal>~/.nix-profile/etc</literal> points to the <literal>nix-2.1.3</literal>
      derivation. At this point, we are in our Nix user profile.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="install-something">
    <title>Install something</title>

    <para>
      Finally something practical! Installation into the Nix environment is an
      interesting process. Let's install <literal>hello</literal>, a simple CLI
      tool which prints <literal>Hello world</literal> and is mainly used to test compilers
      and package installations.
    </para>

    <para>
      Back to the installation:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/install-hello.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Now you can run <literal>hello</literal>. Things to notice:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          We installed software as a user, and only for the Nix user.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          It created a new user environment. That's a new generation of our
          Nix user profile.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <link
          xlink:href="https://nixos.org/manual/nix/stable/command-ref/nix-env.html">nix-env</link>
          tool manages environments, profiles and their generations.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          We installed <literal>hello</literal> by derivation name minus the version. I repeat:
          we specified the <emphasis role="bold">derivation name</emphasis>
          (minus the version) to install it.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      We can list generations without walking through the <filename>/nix</filename> hierarchy:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/list-generations.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Listing installed derivations:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/list-installed-derivations.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      So, where did <literal>hello</literal> really get installed?
      <literal>which hello</literal> is
      <literal>~/.nix-profile/bin/hello</literal> which points to the store.
      We can also list the derivation paths with <command>nix-env -q --out-path</command>. So
      that's what those derivation paths are called: the
      <emphasis role="bold">output</emphasis> of a build.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Path merging</title>

    <para>
      At this point you probably want to run <literal>man</literal> to get some documentation.
      Even if you
      already have man system-wide outside of the Nix environment, you can
      install and use it within Nix with <command>nix-env -i man-db</command>. As
      usual, a new generation will be created, and <filename>~/.nix-profile</filename> will point to
      it.
    </para>

    <para>
      Let's inspect the <link
      xlink:href="https://nixos.org/manual/nix/stable/package-management/profiles.html">profile</link>
      a bit:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/ls-nix-profile.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Now that's interesting. When only <literal>nix-2.1.3</literal> was installed, <filename>bin</filename> was a
      symlink to <literal>nix-2.1.3</literal>. Now that we've actually installed some things
      (<literal>man</literal>, <literal>hello</literal>), it's a real directory, not a symlink.
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/ls-profile-bin.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Okay, that's clearer now. <literal>nix-env</literal> merged the paths from the installed derivations.
      <command>which man</command> points to the Nix profile, rather than the
      system <literal>man</literal>, because <filename>~/.nix-profile/bin</filename> is at the head
      of <varname>$PATH</varname>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Rolling back and switching generation</title>

    <para>
      The last command installed <literal>man</literal>. We should be at generation 3, unless
      you changed something in the middle. Let's say we want to rollback to the
      old generation:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/rollback.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Now <command>nix-env -q</command> does not list <literal>man</literal> anymore.
      <command>ls -l `which man`</command> should now be your system copy.
    </para>

    <para>
      Enough with the rollback, let's go back to the most recent generation:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/generation-3.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      I invite you to read the manpage of <literal>nix-env</literal>. <literal>nix-env</literal> requires an operation
      to perform, then there are common options for all operations, as well as
      options specific to each operation.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can of course also <link
        xlink:href="https://nixos.org/manual/nix/stable/command-ref/nix-env.html#operation---uninstall">
      uninstall</link> and <link
      xlink:href="https://nixos.org/manual/nix/stable/command-ref/nix-env.html#operation---upgrade">upgrade</link> packages.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Querying the store</title>

    <para>
      So far we learned how to query and manipulate the environment. But all
      of the environment components point to the store.
    </para>

    <para>
      To query and manipulate the store, there's the
      <literal>nix-store</literal> command. We can do some interesting things, but we'll
      only see some queries for now.
    </para>

    <para>
      To show the direct runtime dependencies of <literal>hello</literal>:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/references.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      The argument to <literal>nix-store</literal> can be anything as long as it points to the
      Nix store. It will follow symlinks.
    </para>

    <para>
      It may not make sense to you right now, but let's print reverse
      dependencies of <literal>hello</literal>:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/referrers.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Was it what you expected? It turns out that our environments depend upon <literal>hello</literal>.
      Yes, that means that the environments are in the store, and since they contain symlinks to <literal>hello</literal>,
      therefore the environment depends upon <literal>hello</literal>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Two environments were listed, generation 2 and generation 3, since these are the ones that had
      <literal>hello</literal> installed in them.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <filename>manifest.nix</filename> file contains metadata about the environment, such as
      which derivations are installed. So that <literal>nix-env</literal> can list, upgrade
      or remove them. And yet again, the current <filename>manifest.nix</filename> can be found at
      <filename>~/.nix-profile/manifest.nix</filename>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Closures</title>

    <para>
      The closures of a derivation is a list of all its dependencies, recursively,
      including absolutely everything necessary to use that derivation.
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/nix-store.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Copying all those derivations to the Nix store of another machine makes
      you able to run <literal>man</literal> out of the box on that other machine. That's the
      base of deployment using Nix, and you can already foresee the potential when
      deploying software in the cloud (hint:
      <literal>nix-copy-closures</literal> and
      <literal>nix-store --export</literal>).
    </para>

    <para>
      A nicer view of the closure:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/nix-store-tree.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      With the above command, you can find out exactly why a
      <emphasis>runtime</emphasis> dependency, be it direct or
      indirect, exists for a given derivation.
    </para>

    <para>
      The same applies to environments. As an exercise, run
      <command>nix-store -q --tree ~/.nix-profile</command>, and see that the
      first children are direct dependencies of the user environment:
      the installed derivations, and the <filename>manifest.nix</filename>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Dependency resolution</title>

    <para>
      There isn't anything like <literal>apt</literal> which solves a SAT problem in order to
      satisfy dependencies with lower and upper bounds on versions. There's no need
      for this because all the dependencies are static: if a derivation X depends on a derivation Y,
      then it always depends on it. A version of X which depended on Z would be a different derivation.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Recovering the hard way</title>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/uninstall-all.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Oops, that uninstalled all derivations from the environment, including
      Nix. That means  we can't even run <literal>nix-env</literal>, what now?
    </para>

    <para>
      Previously we got <literal>nix-env</literal> from the environment. Environments
      are a convenience for the user, but Nix is still there in the store!
    </para>

    <para>
      First, pick one <literal>nix-2.1.3</literal> derivation:
      <command>ls /nix/store/*nix-2.1.3</command>, say
      <filename>/nix/store/ig31y9gfpp8pf3szdd7d4sf29zr7igbr-nix-2.1.3</filename>.
    </para>

    <para>
      The first option is to rollback:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/nix-env-rollback.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      The second option is to install Nix, thus creating a new generation:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/install.txt" parse="text" /></screen>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Channels</title>

    <para>
      So where are we getting packages from? We said something about this already in the
      <link linkend="install-on-your-running-system">second article</link>.
      There's a list of channels from which we get packages, although usually we use a
      single channel. The tool to manage channels is
      <link xlink:href="https://nixos.org/manual/nix/stable/command-ref/nix-channel.html">nix-channel</link>.
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./03/channel-list.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      If you're using NixOS, you may not see any output from the above command
      (if you're using the default), or you may see a channel whose
      name begins with "nixos-" instead of "nixpkgs".
    </para>

    <para>
      That's essentially the contents of <filename>~/.nix-channels</filename>.
    </para>

    <note><para>
      <filename>~/.nix-channels</filename> is not a symlink to the
      nix store!
    </para></note>

    <para>
      To update the channel run <command>nix-channel --update</command>.
      That will download the new Nix expressions (descriptions of the packages),
      create a new generation of the channels profile and unpack it under
      <filename>~/.nix-defexpr/channels</filename>.
    </para>

    <para>
      This is quite similar to <command>apt-get update</command>.
      (See <link xlink:href="https://nixos.wiki/wiki/Cheatsheet">this table</link>
      for a rough mapping between Ubuntu and NixOS package management.)
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>
      We learned how to query the user environment and to manipulate it by
      installing and uninstalling software. Upgrading software is also straightforward,
      as you can read in
      <link xlink:href="https://nixos.org/manual/nix/stable/command-ref/nix-env.html#operation---upgrade">the manual</link>
      (<command>nix-env -u</command> will upgrade all packages in the
      environment).
    </para>

    <para>
      Every time we change the environment, a new generation is created.
      Switching between generations is easy and immediate.
    </para>

    <para>
      Then we learned how to query the store. We inspected the dependencies and reverse
      dependencies of store paths.
    </para>

    <para>
      We saw how symlinks are used to compose paths from the Nix store, a useful
      trick.
    </para>

    <para>
      A quick analogy with programming languages: you have the heap with all the
      objects, that corresponds to the Nix store. You have objects that point to other
      objects, those correspond to derivations. This is a suggestive metaphor, but will it be the right path?
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Next pill</title>

    <para>
      ...we will learn the basics of the Nix language. The Nix language is used
      to describe how to build derivations, and it's the basis for everything
      else, including NixOS. Therefore it's very important to understand both the
      syntax and the semantics of the language.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
