<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="automatic-runtime-dependencies">

  <title>Automatic Runtime Dependencies</title>

  <para>
    Welcome to the 9th Nix pill. In the previous
    <link linkend="generic-builders">8th pill</link> we wrote a generic builder
    for autotools projects. We feed build dependencies, a source tarball, and
    we get a Nix derivation as a result.
  </para>

  <para>
    Today we stop by the GNU hello world program to analyze build and runtime
    dependencies, and enhance the builder in order to avoid unnecessary runtime
    dependencies.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Build dependencies</title>

    <para>
      Let's start analyzing build dependencies for our GNU hello world package:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./09/instantiate.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      It has exactly the derivations referenced in the <code>derivation</code>
      function, nothing more, nothing less. Some of them might not be used at
      all, however given that our generic mkDerivation function always pulls
      such dependencies (think of it like
      <link xlink:href="https://packages.debian.org/unstable/build-essential">build-essential</link>
      of Debian), for every package you build from now on, you will have these
      packages in the nix store.
    </para>

    <para>
      Why are we looking at .drv files? Because the hello.drv file is the
      representation of the build action to perform in order to build the hello
      out path, and as such it also contains the input derivations needed to be
      built before building hello.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Digression about NAR files</title>

    <para>
      NAR is the Nix ARchive. First question: why not tar? Why another archiver?
      Because commonly used archivers are not deterministic. They add padding,
      they do not sort files, they add timestamps, etc.. Hence NAR, a very
      simple deterministic archive format being used by Nix for deployment.
      NARs are also used extensively within Nix itself as we'll see below.
    </para>

    <para>
      For the rationale and implementation details you can find more in the
      <link xlink:href="http://nixos.org/~eelco/pubs/phd-thesis.pdf">Dolstra's PhD Thesis</link>.
    </para>

    <para>
      To create NAR archives, it's possible to use
      <command>nix-store --dump</command> and
      <command>nix-store --restore</command>. Those two commands work
      regardless of <filename>/nix/store</filename>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Runtime dependencies</title>

    <para>
      Something is different for runtime dependencies however. Build
      dependencies are automatically recognized by Nix once they are used in
      any <code>derivation</code> call, but we never specify what are the
      runtime dependencies for a derivation.
    </para>

    <para>
      There's really black magic involved. It's something that at first glance
      makes you think "no, this can't work in the long term", but at the same
      it works so well that a whole operating system is built on top of this
      magic.
    </para>

    <para>
      In other words, Nix automatically computes all the runtime dependencies
      of a derivation, and it's possible thanks to the hash of the store paths.
    </para>

    <para>
      Steps:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Dump the derivation as NAR, a serialization of the derivation output.
          Works fine whether it's a single file or a directory.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          For each build dependency .drv and its relative out path, search the
          contents of the NAR for this out path.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If found, then it's a runtime dependency.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>
      You get really all the runtime dependencies, and that's why Nix
      deployments are so easy.
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./09/instantiate-hello.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Ok glibc and gcc. Well, gcc really should not be a runtime dependency!
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./09/strings.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Oh Nix added gcc because its out path is mentioned in the "hello" binary.
      Why is that? That's the
      <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rpath">ld rpath</link>.
      It's the list of directories where libraries can be found at runtime. In
      other distributions, this is usually not abused. But in Nix, we have to
      refer to particular versions of libraries, thus the rpath has an
      important role.
    </para>

    <para>
      The build process adds that gcc lib path thinking it may be useful at
      runtime, but really it's not. How do we get rid of it? Nix authors have
      written another magical tool called
      <link xlink:href="https://nixos.org/patchelf.html">patchelf</link>, which
      is able to reduce the rpath to the paths that are really used by the
      binary.
    </para>

    <para>
      Even after reducing the rpath the hello binary would still depend
      upon gcc. This is because of debugging information. To fix is the well
      known <command>strip</command> can be used.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Another phase in the builder</title>

    <para>
      We will add a new phase to our autotools builder. The builder has these
      phases already:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          First the environment is set up
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Unpack phase: we unpack the sources in the current directory
          (remember, Nix changes dir to a temporary directory first)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Change source root to the directory that has been unpacked
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Configure phase: <command>./configure</command>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Build phase: <command>make</command>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Install phase: <command>make install</command>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>
      We add a new phase after the installation phase, which we call
      <emphasis role="bold">fixup</emphasis> phase. At the end of the
      <filename>builder.sh</filename> follows:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./09/find.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      That is, for each file we run <command>patchelf --shrink-rpath</command>
      and <command>strip</command>. Note that we used two new commands here,
      <command>find</command> and <command>patchelf</command>.
      <emphasis role="bold">Exercise:</emphasis> These two
      deserve a place in <code>baseInputs</code> of
      <filename>autotools.nix</filename> as <command>findutils</command> and
      <command>patchelf</command>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Rebuild <filename>hello.nix</filename> and...:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./09/build-hello-nix.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      ...only glibc is the runtime dependency. Exactly what we wanted.
    </para>

    <para>
      The package is self-contained, copy its closure on another machine and
      you will be able to run it. Remember, only a very few components under
      the <filename>/nix/store</filename> are required to
      <link linkend="install-on-your-running-system">run nix</link>.
      The hello binary will use that exact version of glibc library and
      interpreter, not the system one:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./09/ldd-hello.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Of course, the executable runs fine as long as everything is under the
      <filename>/nix/store</filename> path.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>
      Short post compared to previous ones as I'm still on vacation, but I hope
      you enjoyed it. Nix provides tools with cool features. In particular, Nix
      is able to compute all runtime dependencies automatically for us. This is
      not limited to only shared libraries, but also referenced executables,
      scripts, Python libraries etc..
    </para>

    <para>
      This makes packages self-contained, ensuring (apart data and
      configuration) that copying the runtime closure on another machine is
      sufficient to run the program. That's why Nix has
      <link xlink:href="https://nixos.org/nix/manual/#ch-relnotes-0.8">one-click install</link>,
      or
      <link xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nixops/manual/#chap-introduction">reliable deployment in the cloud</link>.
      All with one tool.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Next pill</title>

    <para>
      ...we will introduce nix-shell. With nix-build we always build
      derivations from scratch: the source gets unpacked, configured, built
      and installed. But this may take a long time, think of WebKit. What if we
      want to apply some small changes and compile incrementally instead, yet
      keeping a self-contained environment similar to nix-build?
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
