<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      version="5.0"
      xml:id="developing-with-nix-shell">

  <title>Developing with <command>nix-shell</command></title>

  <para>
    Welcome to the 10th Nix pill. In the previous
    <link linkend="automatic-runtime-dependencies">9th pill</link> we saw
    one of the powerful features of Nix: automatic discovery of runtime
    dependencies. We also finalized the GNU <code>hello</code> package.
  </para>

  <para>
    In this pill, we will introduce the <command>nix-shell</command> tool
    and use it to hack on the GNU <code>hello</code> program. We will
    see how <command>nix-shell</command> gives us an isolated environment
    while we modify the source files of the project, similar to how
    <command>nix-build</command> gave us an isolated environment while building
    the derivation.
  </para>

  <para>
    Finally, we will modify our builder to work more ergonomically
    with a <command>nix-shell</command>-focused workflow.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>What is <command>nix-shell</command>?</title>

    <para>
      The <link
      xlink:href="https://nixos.org/manual/nix/stable/command-ref/nix-shell.html">nix-shell</link>
      tool drops us in a shell after setting up the environment variables necessary
      to hack on a derivation. It does not build the derivation; it
      only serves as a preparation so that we can run the build steps manually.
    </para>

    <para>
      Recall that in a nix environment, we don't have access to libraries or
      programs unless they have been installed with <command>nix-env</command>.
      However, installing libraries with <command>nix-env</command> is not
      good practice. We prefer to have isolated environments for development, which
      <command>nix-shell</command> provides for us.
    </para>

    <para>
      We can call <command>nix-shell</command> on any Nix expression which
      returns a derivation, but the resulting <code>bash</code> shell's
      <code>PATH</code> does not have the utilities we want:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./10/nix-shell-hello.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      This shell is rather useless. It would be reasonable to expect that the GNU
      <code>hello</code> build inputs are available in <code>PATH</code>, including
      GNU <code>make</code>, but this is not the case.
    </para>

    <para>
      However, we do have the environment variables that we set in the derivation,
      like <code>$baseInputs</code>, <code>$buildInputs</code>,
      <code>$src</code>, and so on.
    </para>

    <para>
      This means that we can <command>source</command> our
      <filename>builder.sh</filename>, and it will build the derivation.
      You may get an error in the installation phase, because your user may
      not have the permission to write to <filename>/nix/store</filename>:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./10/source-builder.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      The derivation didn't install, but it did build. Note the following:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          We sourced <filename>builder.sh</filename> and it ran all of the build
          steps, including setting up the <code>PATH</code> for us.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The working directory is no longer a temp directory created by
          <command>nix-build</command>, but is instead the directory in which
          we entered the shell. Therefore, <filename>hello-2.10</filename> has
          been unpacked in the current directory.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      We are able to <command>cd</command> into <filename>hello-2.10</filename> and type
      <command>make</command>, because <command>make</command> is now available.
    </para>

    <para>
      The take-away is that <command>nix-shell</command> drops us in a shell with the
      same (or very similar) environment used to run the builder.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>A builder for nix-shell</title>

    <para>
      The previous steps require some manual commands to be run and are not
      optimized for a workflow centered on <command>nix-shell</command>. We
      will now improve our builder to be more <command>nix-shell</command> friendly.
    </para>

    <para>
      There are a few things that we would like to change.
    </para>

    <para>
      First, when we <command>source</command>d the <filename>builder.sh</filename>
      file, we obtained the file in the current directory. What we really wanted
      was the <filename>builder.sh</filename> that is stored in the nix store,
      as this is the file that would be used by <command>nix-build</command>.
      To achieve this, the correct technique is to pass an environment variable
      through the derivation. (Note that <code>$builder</code> is
      already defined, but it points to the bash executable rather than our
      <filename>builder.sh</filename>. Our <filename>builder.sh</filename> is
      passed as an argument to bash.)
    </para>

    <para>
      Second, we don't want to run the whole builder: we only want to setup
      the necessary environment for manually building the project. Thus, we
      can break <filename>builder.sh</filename> into two files: a
      <filename>setup.sh</filename> for setting up the environment, and
      the real <filename>builder.sh</filename> that <command>nix-build</command>
      expects.
    </para>

    <para>
      During our refactoring, we will wrap the build phases in functions to
      give more structure to our design. Additionally, we'll move the
      <code>set -e</code> to the builder file instead of the setup file.
      The <code>set -e</code> is annoying in <command>nix-shell</command>,
      as it will terminate the shell if an error is encountered (such as
      a mistyped command.)
    </para>

    <para>
      Here is our modified <filename>autotools.nix</filename>.
      Noteworthy is the <code>setup = ./setup.sh;</code> attribute in the
      derivation, which adds <filename>setup.sh</filename> to the nix store and
      correspondingly adds a <code>$setup</code> environment variable in the builder.
    </para>

    <programlisting><xi:include href="./10/autotools-nix.txt" parse="text" /></programlisting>

    <para>
      Thanks to that, we can split <filename>builder.sh</filename> into
      <filename>setup.sh</filename> and <filename>builder.sh</filename>. What
      <filename>builder.sh</filename> does is <command>source</command>
      <code>$setup</code> and call the <code>genericBuild</code> function.
      Everything else is just some changes to the bash script.
    </para>

    <para>
      Here is the modified <filename>builder.sh</filename>:
    </para>

    <programlisting><xi:include href="./10/builder-sh.txt" parse="text" /></programlisting>

    <para>
      Here is the newly added <filename>setup.sh</filename>:
    </para>

    <programlisting><xi:include href="./10/setup-sh.txt" parse="text" /></programlisting>

    <para>
      Finally, here is <filename>hello.nix</filename>:
    </para>

    <programlisting><xi:include href="./10/hello-nix.txt" parse="text" /></programlisting>

    <para>
      Now back to nix-shell:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./10/nix-shell-source.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Now, for example, you can run <code>unpackPhase</code> which unpacks
      <code>$src</code> and enters the directory. And you can run commands
      like <command>./configure</command>, <command>make</command>, and so forth
      manually, or run phases with their respective functions.
    </para>

    <para>
      The process is that straightforward. <command>nix-shell</command> builds the
      <code>.drv</code> file and its input dependencies, then drops into a shell
      by setting up the environment variables necessary to build the <code>.drv</code>.
      In particular, the environment variables in the shell match those passed
      to the <code>derivation</code> function.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>
      With <command>nix-shell</command> we are able to drop into an isolated
      environment suitable for developing a project. This environment provides the necessary
      dependencies for the development shell, similar to how
      <command>nix-build</command> provides the necessary dependencies to a builder.
      Additionally, we can build and debug the project manually, executing step-by-step
      like we would in any other operating system. Note that we never installed tools
      such <command>gcc</command> or <command>make</command> system-wide; these tools
      and libraries are isolated and available per-build.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Next pill</title>

    <para>
      In the next pill, we will clean up the nix store. We have written and built
      derivations which add to the nix store, but until now we haven't worried
      about cleaning up the used space in the store.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
