<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      version="5.0"
      xml:id="developing-with-nix-shell">

  <title>Developing with <command>nix-shell</command></title>

  <para>
    Welcome to the 10th Nix pill. In the previous
    <link linkend="automatic-runtime-dependencies">9th pill</link> we saw
    one of the powerful features of nix, automatic discovery of runtime
    dependencies and finalized the GNU hello world package.
  </para>

  <para>
    Having returned from vacation, we want to hack a little the GNU hello
    world program. The nix-build tool allows for an isolated environment
    while building the derivation. Additionally, we'd like the same
    isolation in order to modify some source files of the project.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>What's nix-shell</title>

    <para>
      The <link
      xlink:href="https://nixos.org/manual/nix/stable/command-ref/nix-shell.html">nix-shell</link>
      tool drops us in a shell by setting up the necessary environment
      variables to hack on a derivation. It does not build the derivation, it
      only serves as a preparation so that we can run the build steps manually.
    </para>

    <para>
      I remind you, in a nix environment you don't have access to libraries and
      programs unless you install them with nix-env. However installing
      libraries with nix-env is not good practice. We prefer to have isolated
      environments for development.
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./10/nix-shell-hello.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      First thing to notice, we call <command>nix-shell</command> on a nix
      expression which returns a derivation. We then enter a new bash shell,
      but it's really useless. We expected to have the GNU hello world build
      inputs available in PATH, including GNU make, but it's not the case.
    </para>

    <para>
      But, we have the environment variables that we set in the derivation,
      like <code>$baseInputs</code>, <code>$buildInputs</code>,
      <code>$src</code> and so on.
    </para>

    <para>
      That means we can source our <filename>builder.sh</filename>, and it will
      build the derivation. You may get an error in the installation phase,
      because the user may not have the permission to write to
      <filename>/nix/store</filename>:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./10/source-builder.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      It didn't install, but it built. Things to notice:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          We sourced builder.sh, therefore it ran all the steps including
          setting up the PATH for us.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The working directory is no more a temp directory created by nix-build, but the current directory. Therefore, hello-2.10 has been unpacked there.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      We're able to <command>cd</command> into hello-2.10 and type
      <command>make</command>, because now it's available.
    </para>

    <para>
      In other words, <command>nix-shell</command> drops us in a shell with the
      same (or almost) environment used to run the builder!
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>A builder for nix-shell</title>

    <para>
      The previous steps are a bit annoying of course, but we can improve our
      builder to be more nix-shell friendly.
    </para>

    <para>
      First of all, we were able to source <filename>builder.sh</filename>
      because it was in our current directory, but that's not nice. We want the
      <filename>builder.sh</filename> that is stored in the nix store, the one
      that would be used by <command>nix-build</command>. To do so, the right
      way is to pass the usual environment variable through the derivation.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis role="underlined">Note</emphasis>: <code>$builder</code> is
      already defined, but it's the bash executable, not our
      <filename>builder.sh</filename>. Our <filename>builder.sh</filename> is
      an argument to bash.
    </para>

    <para>
      Second, we don't want to run the whole builder, we only want it to setup
      the necessary environment for manually building the project. So we'll
      write two files, one for setting up the environment, and the real
      <filename>builder.sh</filename> that runs with
      <command>nix-build</command>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Additionally, we'll wrap the phases in functions, it may be useful, and
      move the <code>set -e</code> to the builder instead of the setup. The
      <code>set -e</code> is annoying in <command>nix-shell</command>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Here is our modified <filename>autotools.nix</filename>.
      Noteworthy is the <code>setup = ./setup.sh;</code> attribute in the
      derivation, which adds <filename>setup.sh</filename> to the nix store and
      as usual, adds a <code>$setup</code> environment variable in the builder.
    </para>

    <programlisting><xi:include href="./10/autotools-nix.txt" parse="text" /></programlisting>

    <para>
      Thanks to that, we can split <filename>builder.sh</filename> into
      <filename>setup.sh</filename> and <filename>builder.sh</filename>. What
      <filename>builder.sh</filename> does is sourcing <code>$setup</code> and
      calling the <code>genericBuild</code> function. Everything else is just
      some bash changes.
    </para>

    <para>
      Here is the modified <filename>builder.sh</filename>.
    </para>

    <programlisting><xi:include href="./10/builder-sh.txt" parse="text" /></programlisting>

    <para>
      Here is the newly added <filename>setup.sh</filename>.
    </para>

    <programlisting><xi:include href="./10/setup-sh.txt" parse="text" /></programlisting>

    <para>
      Finally, here is <filename>hello.nix</filename>.
    </para>

    <programlisting><xi:include href="./10/hello-nix.txt" parse="text" /></programlisting>

    <para>
      Now back to nix-shell:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./10/nix-shell-source.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Now you can run, for example, <code>unpackPhase</code> which unpacks
      <code>$src</code> and enters the directory. And you can run commands
      like <command>./configure</command>, <command>make</command> etc.
      manually, or run phases with their respective functions.
    </para>

    <para>
      It's that straightforward, <command>nix-shell</command> builds the .drv file
      and its input dependencies, then drops into a shell by setting up the
      environment variables necessary to build the .drv, in particular those
      passed to the derivation function.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>
      With <command>nix-shell</command> we're able to drop into an isolated
      environment for developing a project, with the necessary dependencies
      just like <command>nix-build</command> does. Additionally, we can build and
      debug the project manually, step by step like you would do in any other
      operating system. Note that we never installed <command>gcc</command>,
      <command>make</command>, etc. system-wide. These tools and libraries are
      available per-build.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Next pill</title>

    <para>
      ...we will clean up the nix store. We wrote and built derivations, added
      stuff to nix store, but until now we never worried about cleaning up the
      used space in the store. It's time to collect some garbage.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
