<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="fundamentals-of-stdenv">

  <title>fundamentals of stdenv</title>

  <para>
    Welcome to the 19th Nix pill. In the previous <link linkend="nix-store-paths">18th</link> pill we did dive into the algorithm used by Nix to compute the store paths, and also introduced fixed-output store paths.
  </para>

  <para>
    This time we will instead look into <literal>nixpkgs</literal>, in particular one of its core derivation: <literal>stdenv</literal>.
  </para>

  <para>
    The <literal>stdenv</literal> is not a special derivation, but it's very important for the <literal>nixpkgs</literal> repository. It serves as base for packaging software. It is used to pull in dependencies such as the GCC toolchain, GNU make, core utilities, patch and diff utilities, and so on. Basic tools needed to compile a huge pile of software currently present in <literal>nixpkgs</literal>.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>What is stdenv</title>

    <para>
      First of all <literal>stdenv</literal> is a derivation. And it's a very simple one:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./19/stdenv-derivation.txt" parse="text" /></screen>
    <para>
      It has just two files: <filename>/setup</filename> and <filename>/nix-support/propagated-user-env-packages</filename>. Don't care about the latter, it's even empty. The important file is <filename>/setup</filename>.
    </para>

    <para>
      How can this simple derivation pull in all the toolchain and basic tools needed to compile packages? Let's look at the runtime dependencies:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./19/stdenv-references.txt" parse="text" /></screen>
    <para>
      How can it be? The package must be referring to those package somehow. In fact, they are hardcoded in the <filename>/setup</filename> file:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./19/stdenv-setup-head.txt" parse="text" /></screen>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The setup file</title>

    <para>
      Remember our generic <filename>builder.sh</filename> in <link linkend="generic-builders">Pill 8</link>? It sets up a basic <varname>PATH</varname>, unpacks the source and runs the usual <package>autotools</package> commands for us.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <literal>stdenv</literal> <filename>setup</filename> file is exactly that. It sets up several environment variables like <varname>PATH</varname> and creates some helper bash functions to build a package. I invite you to read it, it's only 860 lines at the time of this writing.
    </para>

    <para>
      The hardcoded toolchain and utilities are used to initially fill up the environment variables so that it's more pleasant to run common commands, similarly but not equal like we did with our builder with <literal>baseInputs</literal> and <literal>buildInputs</literal>.
    </para>

    <para>
      The build with <literal>stdenv</literal> works in phases. Phases are like <literal>unpackPhase</literal>, <literal>configurePhase</literal>, <literal>buildPhase</literal>, <literal>checkPhase</literal>, <literal>installPhase</literal>, <literal>fixupPhase</literal>. You can see the default list in the <literal>genericBuild</literal> function.
    </para>

    <para>
      What <literal>genericBuild</literal> does is just run these phases. Default phases are just bash functions, you can easily read them.
    </para>

    <para>
      Every phase has hooks to run commands before and after the phase has been executed. Phases can be overwritten, reordered, whatever, it's just bash code.
    </para>

    <para>
      How to use this file? Like our old builder. To test it, we enter a fake empty derivation, source the <literal>stdenv</literal> <filename>setup</filename>, unpack the hello sources and build it:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./19/stdenv-setup-fake-builder.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      <emphasis role="italic">I unset <varname>PATH</varname> to further show that the <literal>stdenv</literal> is enough self-contained to build autotools packages that have no other dependencies.</emphasis>
    </para>

    <para>
      So we ran the <literal>configurePhase</literal> function and <literal>buildPhase</literal> function and they worked. These bash functions should be self-explanatory, you can read the code in the <filename>setup</filename> file.
    </para>

  </section>
  <section>
    <title>How is the setup file built</title>

    <para>
      Until now we worked with plain bash scripts. What about the Nix side? The <literal>nixpkgs</literal> repository offers a useful function, like we did with our old builder. It is a wrapper around the raw derivation function which pulls in the <literal>stdenv</literal> for us, and runs <literal>genericBuild</literal>. It's <literal>stdenv.mkDerivation</literal>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Note how <literal>stdenv</literal> is a derivation but it's also an attribute set which contains some other attributes, like <literal>mkDerivation</literal>. Nothing fancy here, just convenience.
    </para>

    <para>
      Let's write a <filename>hello.nix</filename> expression using this new discovered <literal>stdenv</literal>:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./19/stdenv-hello.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Don't be scared by the <literal>with</literal> expression. It pulls the <literal>nixpkgs</literal> repository into scope, so we can directly use <literal>stdenv</literal>. It looks very similar to the hello expression in <link linkend="generic-builders">Pill 8</link>.
    </para>

    <para>
      It builds, and runs fine:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./19/stdenv-hello-build.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The stdenv.mkDerivation builder</title>

    <para>
      Let's take a look at the builder used by <literal>mkDerivation</literal>. You can read the code <link xlink:href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/blob/master/pkgs/stdenv/generic/default.nix#L155">here in nixpkgs</link>:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./19/stdenv-mkderivation.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      Also take a look at our old derivation wrapper in previous pills! The builder is bash (that shell variable), the argument to the builder (bash) is <filename>default-builder.sh</filename>, and then we add the environment variable <literal>$stdenv</literal> in the derivation which is the <literal>stdenv</literal> derivation.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can open <link xlink:href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/blob/master/pkgs/stdenv/generic/default-builder.sh">default-builder.sh</link> and see what it does:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./19/default-builder.txt" parse="text" /></screen>

    <para>
      It's what we did in <link linkend="developing-with-nix-shell">Pill 10</link> to make the derivations <literal>nix-shell</literal> friendly. When entering the shell, the setup file only sets up the environment without building anything. When doing <literal>nix-build</literal>, it actually runs the build process.
    </para>

    <para>
      To get a clear understanding of the environment variables, look at the .drv of the hello derivation:
    </para>

    <screen><xi:include href="./19/hello-derivation.txt" parse="text" /></screen>
    <para>
      So short I decided to paste it entirely above. The builder is bash, with <literal>-e default-builder.sh</literal> arguments. Then you can see the <literal>src</literal> and <literal>stdenv</literal> environment variables.
    </para>

    <para>
      Last bit, the <literal>unpackPhase</literal> in the setup is used to unpack the sources and enter the directory, again like we did in our old builder.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>
      The <literal>stdenv</literal> is the core of the <literal>nixpkgs</literal> repository. All packages use the <literal>stdenv.mkDerivation</literal> wrapper instead of the raw derivation. It does a bunch of operations for us and also sets up a pleasant build environment.
    </para>

    <para>
      The overall process is simple:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><command>nix-build</command></para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><command>bash -e default-builder.sh</command></para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><command>source $stdenv/setup</command></para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><command>genericBuild</command></para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      That's it, everything you need to know about the stdenv phases is in the <link xlink:href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/blob/master/pkgs/stdenv/generic/setup.sh">setup file</link>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Really, take your time to read that file. Don't forget that juicy docs are also available in the <link xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nixpkgs/manual/#chap-stdenv">nixpkgs manual</link>.
    </para>

  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Next pill...</title>

    <para>
      ...we will talk about how to add dependencies to our packages, <literal>buildInputs</literal>, <literal>propagatedBuildInputs</literal> and <literal>setup</literal> hooks. These three concepts are at the base of the current <literal>nixpkgs</literal> packages composition.
    </para>

  </section>
</chapter>
